Guide to the Atlanta Lesbian Feminist Alliance Archives, ca. 1972-1994 RL.00022
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Atlanta Lesbian Feminist Alliance (ALFA) Archives
circa 1972-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Atlanta Lesbian Feminist Alliance
RL.00022
24 Linear Feet
18,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Atlanta Lesbian Feminist Alliance (ALFA) Archives were purchased and transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1994.
Historical Note
The Atlanta Lesbian Feminist Alliance (ALFA) was founded in 1972 by a group of radical lesbians, many socialist and all feminist, who broke away from Atlanta's Women's Liberation Center and the Gay Liberation movement because they felt that neither had adequately addressed issues of concern to women as lesbians and lesbians as women. ALFA initially worked to fill a social void for and to offer a political voice to Atlanta lesbians, publicizing its efforts through a self-produced monthly newsletter, the Atalanta. Over the years, as the political and cultural climate changed and lesbians created new avenues through which to pursue their interests, ALFA struggled to find a clear and unique sense of purpose; this historically telling struggle is well-documented by ALFA itself, in minutes and mailings to its membership. In spite of its eventual decision to disband, ALFA remains known as one of the oldest lesbian feminist organizations in the United States, and a pioneer in the fight for lesbian, gay, and women's rights.
One of the activities of ALFA--deeply concerned from the outset with the preservation of lesbian "herstory"--was to build and maintain the Southern Feminist Library and Archives (SFLA). The library and archives, which provided a material link between ALFA and other progressive movements and organizations throughout the world, included the archival records of ALFA and several other southern feminist groups; a massive collection of feminist, lesbian, and activist periodicals; and a circulating library of feminist and gay and lesbian books. ALFA disbanded in 1994 after over 20 years of Southern feminist activism.
Collection Overview
When ALFA disbanded in 1994, the archival collections and the bulk of the periodicals collection were transferred to Duke's David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. The book collection and the remaining periodicals stayed in Atlanta, with books relating to feminist theory going to Emory University and the rest to a community library. The ALFA Archives and Periodicals Collections that have been transferred to Duke are an incredibly rich source of information about feminist and lesbian activism and communities, especially in the Southeast, from the early 1970s to the present.
The ALFA Archives includes the organizational records of ALFA as well as other southern radical women's groups such as Lucina's Music/Orchid Productions; Radio Free Georgia (WRFG) women's programming; the womonwrites conference for lesbian writers and publishers; the Southern Women's Music festival; the Atlanta Socialist-Feminist Women's Union; and Dykes for the Second American Revolution (DAR II). The extensive subject files, which are a part of ALFA's archives, document scores of other feminist, lesbian, and activist organizations and events as well as provide information on a broad range of feminist and lesbian issues. Of particular note are ALFA's "Theory/Analysis (Women)" files, as well as their collection of publications by KNOW, Inc., in the "Publishers" subseries; using these primary materials, researchers can get a good sense of the issues that gave rise to the women's liberation movement and to ALFA in the late 1960s and early 1970s.
The ALFA Periodicals Collection contains literally hundreds of grassroots newsletters and journals, many of which are now ephemeral and not in any library. This extensive library of feminist, lesbian and gay, and activist periodicals is more fully described in a separate guide.
Processing Note
For the most part, the original order of the ALFA Archives was maintained after being transferred to Duke. Several boxes, which had been in storage and never fully processed by ALFA, were organized upon arrival at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. Minor rearrangement and consolidation of some of the ALFA records and subject files helped to reduce confusion and highlight areas of strength. The following container list was created to give maximum access to an incredibly dense and rich collection of information.
Feminist theory; Women political activists -- United States; Lesbian activists -- Southern States; Lesbian music; Feminist music; Feminism -- Southern States -- Societies, etc.; Women -- Southern States; Gay liberation movement -- Southern States; Lesbianism -- United States; Lesbianism -- Georgia; Lesbians -- Southern States; Gay activists -- Southern States; Lesbian activists -- United States; Feminism -- Georgia; Gay liberation movement -- United States; Atlanta Socialist-Feminist Union; Lucina's Music; Orchid Productions; Southern Women's Music Festival
- Administrative Files Series
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains material pertaining to the daily workings of ALFA, including events ALFA sponsored or participated in and the publicity for these events; information about individual members; fundraising for the organization; committees within the organization; meetings; correspondence; information about the Southern Feminist Library and Archives; and Atalanta, ALFA's newsletter.
  - General Files Subseries (Box 1)
    - File Lists for Library Files (Box 1)
    - Foremothers (Box 1)
    - ALFA Members Past and Present
      [press clippings on individual members]
      - Elizabeth (Betty) Irwin Burdette, 1919-1988 (Box 1)
      - Vicki Gabriner, 1942- (Box 1)
      - Pamela Jo Martin, 1945-1989 (Box 1)
    - Activities (Box 1)
      [announcements of progressive events, sent to ALFA; correspondence from ALFA re: fundraising projects; newsletters, benefit announcements, press releases (no chronological order)]
    - Activity flyers (Box 1)
    - Great SE Lesbian Conference (Box 1)
    - Take Back our Rights [12/15/91] (Box 1)
    - ALFA Cat Show [see also photographs in Box 19] (Box 1)
    - Potluck Dinner Discussion, 1/85: "Is ALFA a feminist organization?" (Box 1)
      [audio cassette & revised "Statement of Being" resulting from discussion]
    - Raffle ticket originals (Box 1)
    - Book collection and review assignments (Box 1)
    - Contact dykes (Box 1)
      [handouts for women new in area - includes maps of Atlanta, transport and lodging information; information about locales of interest to gays, lesbians and feminists; and the "Directory of Contact Dykes"]
    - Grants
      - Reference info (Box 1)
      - Sources/Application Forms (Box 1)
      - Fundraising (Box 1)
    - Herstory of ALFA [includes ALFA lesbian timeline] (Box 1)
    - Telephone logs - incoming calls 1974-1989 (Box 1)
      Arrangement note
      [out-of-sequence]
    - Incorporation: An initial study for the ALFA to determine the feasibility of incorporation as a non-profit (Box 1)
    - Originals of forms (Box 1)
    - Post Office (Box 1)
    - Printing (Box 1)
    - Questionnaires sent to ALFA from other organizations (Box 1)
    - Returned mail (Box 1)
    - ALFA Resource List for Volunteers (Box 1)
    - 1973 ALFA Survey (Box 1)
      [sent to members and/or affiliates in order to"establish stronger direction for ALFA, to reach a broader range of women."]
    - Phone tree (Box 1)
    - 10th birthday bash [see also Box 19 and oversize folders for photographs] (Box 1)
    - Other ALFA Birthday Celebrations (Box 1)
    - ALFA Lesbian Timeline (Box 1)
  - Committees Subseries (Box 2)
    - Misc. (Box 2)
    - Boogiewimmin (social committee), 1 folder, which also contains 1 red divided notebook (Box 2)
    - Finance (Box 2)
    - Fund for Southern Communities (Box 2)
    - House (Box 2)
    - House key (Box 2)
    - House renovations (Box 2)
    - Speaker's Bureau (Box 2)
    - Speaker's Bureau Packet (Box 2)
    - Library [See also SFLA files, Box 5]
      - Library Directory Listings of ALFA (Box 2)
      - Library Mail Answered and Waiting for Reply (Box 2)
      - Library Newsletter (Box 2)
      - Library Reading List (Box 2)
    - Media [See also "Media" subject files, Box 11]
      - Media Resource Addresses (Box 2)
      - Media How-to's (Box 2)
      - Bird's Coverage of ALFA and Lesbian Activities (Box 2)
        [The Great Speckled Bird is/was a weekly publication of the Atlanta Cooperative News Project] Mostly clippings; a couple of complete issues
      - Media Correspondence: Radio, TV Stations (Box 2)
        [letters from ALFA, most protesting depictions of lesbians and gays in film and TV]
      - ALFA ( Journal/Constitution ) (Box 2)
        [includes originals and copies of correspondence from ALFA, to the 2 Atlanta papers, protesting the lack of coverage of ALFA events and gay/lesbian issues in particular; and correspondence to ALFA, from the two papers, in response to ALFA: March 6 1973-7/9/73]
    - Membership
      - New Member Packet (Box 2)
        [includes house and key rules, description of ALFA library and archive, list of committees]
      - "Old" New Member Packet (Box 2)
      - Originals for Prospective Member Packet (Box 2)
      - Member Letter and New Member Packets (Box 2)
      - Membership Lists (Box 2)
      - Membership Forms (Box 2)
      - Pledge Forms, Blank (Box 2)
      - Pledge Forms
        - 1990 (Box 2)
        - 1988 (Box 2)
        - 1977/8-1985, 8 folders (Box 2)
      - Newsletter ( Atalanta ) (Box 2)
      - Artwork (Box 2)
      - Return to Artist (Box 2)
      - Checklist (Box 2)
      - Covers (Box 2)
      - Leftover Stuff (Box 2)
      - Production (Box 2)
    - Outreach coordinator (See also "Staff Person/Intern" folders) (Box 2)
  - Staff Person/Intern Series, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Antioch Intern correspondence (Box 2)
    - Antioch Intern (Box 2)
      [lists duties, includes job summary sheets and evaluations of ALFA by several interns, and the notebook of intern Barbara McCann, 4-10/1981]
    - Staff Person 82-3 (Box 2)
      [details duties of outreach coordinator (see also Box 2, "Outreach Coordinator" folder)]
    - "Staff Program to DateDecember 6, 1981" (Box 2)
      [lists accomplishments to date/planning for different committees, e.g., Speaker's bureau, Jewish Cultural Workshop, New Members workshop]
  - Correspondence to ALFA Subseries (Box 3)
    - 1970s (Box 3)
    - 1973-1994 (Box 3)
      Each year or years subdivided into 2 categories:
      1) Correspondence from individuals
      2) Correspondence from groups
      [NOTE: There is also a file containing the letters of an individual named "Rosemary Curb" in the "Individual" section of 1986.]
  - Indexing Project Subseries, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Periodicals/Subscriptions Subseries, 3 folders, 1 notebook
    - Subscription correspondence from ALFA (Box 4)
    - Exchange agreements (Box 4)
    - Exchange requests (Box 4)
    - Inventory, 1 red spiral notebook (Box 4)
  - Southern Feminist Library & Archives (SFLA) Subseries (Box 5)
    - Board of Directors (Box 5)
    - Correspondence to SFLA re: fundraising (Box 5)
    - Fundraising (Box 5)
    - Grant submitted to the National March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights (Box 5)
    - House (Box 5)
    - Legal Documents (bylaws and incorporation) (Box 5)
    - Newsletter (Box 5)
    - Posters (Box 5)
    - Statement of Purpose (Box 5)
    - Stationery (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Subseries (ALFA Newsletter), 1973-1994, 22 folders (Box 6)
  - Mail Check-In Logs Subseries, 7/2/74 - 8/10/91, 15 volumes (Box 7)
  - ALFA Meeting Minutes Subseries, 3 volumes
    - 1972- (Box 7)
    - 1982- (Box 7)
    - 1990- (Box 7)
      [including last report/newsletter explaining ALFA's closure]
- Subject Files Series
  Files in this series fall roughly into two categories: 1) material sent to ALFA by women's, lesbian and gay organizations, including information about the organizations themselves or about events each sponsored; and 2) papers, newspaper and journal clippings, etc. on issues affecting women, lesbians and gays.
  - Local Women's Groups Subseries (Box 8)
    - Africana Women's Center (Box 8)
    - Aid to Imprisoned Mothers (Box 8)
    - Amazons Softball (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Feminist Women's Chorus (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Lesbian Agenda Conference (1/90) [See also "National Lesbian Conference" files, Box 9] (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Women's Art Collective, Inc. (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Women's Coffeehouse and Granny May Productions (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Women's Liberation Group (Box 8)
    - Task Force on Battered Women (Box 8)
    - Feminist Women's Health Center (Box 8)
    - GERA (Georgians for the Equal Rights Amendment) (Box 8)
    - HEART (Health, Education and Art) Women's Center of Atlanta (Box 8)
    - Karuna Atlanta Women's Counseling Collective (Box 8)
    - LEAP (Lesbians for Empowerment, Action and Politics) (Box 8)
    - Lucina's Music [see also Box 24] (Box 8)
    - Matrix Music (Box 8)
    - National Black Women's Health Project [headquartered in Atlanta] (Box 8)
    - NOW Atlanta
      - Connections [Lesbian Task Force of NOW Atlanta] (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Nine to Five (Box 8)
    - Orchid Productions [see also Boxes 23-24] (Box 8)
    - Red Dyke Theater (Box 8)
    - Sisters (Box 8)
    - SE Lesbian Network (Box 8)
    - SE Women's Studies Association (Box 8)
    - Spelman: Women's Research and Resource Center (Box 8)
    - Womansong Theater (Box 8)
    - Women Against Military Madness (WAMM) (Box 8)
    - Women of Wisdom (WOW) (Box 8)
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom [See also "International Women's Groups", Box 9] (Box 8)
    - Women's Studies Association, Atlanta (Box 8)
    - YWCA Atlanta (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Lesbian Bars (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Lesbian Events (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Lesbian Theater Groups (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Lesbian Readings (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Lesbian Women's Writers (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Women's Activities (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Women's Groups (Box 8)
    - Atlanta Women's Theater (Box 8)
    - Georgia Lesbians (Box 8)
    - Georgia Women's Groups, Misc. (Box 8)
    - Southeast Women's Activities (Box 8)
    - Southeast Women's Events (Box 8)
    - Southeast Women's Groups (Box 8)
  - Local Women's Issues Subseries
    - Abortion/Reproductive Rights (Box 8)
    - ERA [See also "GERA" file under Local Women's Groups] (Box 8)
    - Women's Spirituality and Creativity (Box 8)
    - Women in Higher Education (Box 8)
    - Women in History (Box 8)
    - Rape (Box 8)
    - Self-Defense (Box 8)
    - Peace Movement (Box 8)
    - Women and Work (Box 8)
  - Local Non-woman/Non-gay Subseries (Box 8)
    - Little 5 PointsGroups and Activities (Box 8)
    - Labor, Union struggles (Box 8)
    - Civil Rights, Anti-Klan (Box 8)
      [includes 1982 Special Report, The Ku Klux Klan: A History of Racism and Violence, pub. by the Southern Poverty Law Center; and A Non-Violent Action Manual, William Moyer, New Society Press, 1977 ]
    - Police Brutality (black community) (Box 8)
    - Anti-nuke and Georgia Power (Box 8)
    - Third World Countries' Struggles (South America) (Box 8)
      [NOTE: This file pertains only to Atlantans' efforts on behalf of third world countries - see also "Third World Women's Groups" files below.]
    - Prisons (Box 8)
    - Political Parties (Socialist, Communist) (Box 8)
    - Nixon and Ford (Box 8)
    - Local non-gay and non-women eventsmisc. (Box 8)
  - Regional Women's Groups Subseries (See "Local Women's Groups" for organizations in the Southeast) (Box 9)
    - Eastern Women's Groups (Box 9)
    - Eastern Women's Events and Activities (Box 9)
    - Lesbian Feminist Liberation (NYC) (Box 9)
    - Eastern Lesbian Groups and Events (Box 9)
    - Midwest Women's Groups (Box 9)
    - Midwest Women's Events and Activities (Box 9)
    - Midwest Lesbian Groups and Events (Box 9)
    - West Women's Groups and Events (Box 9)
    - West Women's Activities and Events (Box 9)
    - West Lesbian groups and Events (Box 9)
  - National Women's Groups
    - Evangelical Women's Caucus (Box 9)
      [includes manifesto, booklist]
    - Directories, Lists, Etc. of Women's Groups in the US (Box 9)
    - International Women's Day 1992 (Box 9)
    - Mormons for ERA (Box 9)
    - National Black Women's Health Project [see "Local Women's Groups"] (Box 9)
    - National Conference on Socialist-Feminism, Antioch College, 1975 (Box 9)
    - National Lesbian Conference (pre-1991) (Box 9)
    - First National Lesbian Conference, 24-28 April 1991 (Box 9)
      [includes press clippings, program, handouts from ind. panels, including that of Queer Nation/NY, history of conference]
    - National Lesbian Feminist Organization (Box 9)
    - National Lesbian Happenings (Box 9)
    - NOW [see also NOW Atlanta] (Box 9)
    - National Women's Conferences (Box 9)
    - National Women's Events (Box 9)
    - National Women's Groups (Other) (Box 9)
      [includes An Analysis of Sacaris, Inc., by the August 7th Survival Community a radical offshoot of Sacaris, Lyndon State College, Lyndonville, VT; Womanhood in America, 1776-1976, a publication of the Northwest Georgia Girl Scout Council]
    - National Women and Govt. Lobbies (Box 9)
    - National Women's Political Caucus (NWPC) (Box 9)
    - NWPC Conference, 6/29/85, Atlanta (Box 9)
      [includes material about the dance that ALFA & WOW co-sponsored]
    - Women's Motorcycle Foundation (Box 9)
    - Women Against Pornography (Box 9)
  - International Women's Groups Subseries
    - Canada Women's movements (Box 9)
    - Europe (Box 9)
    - ILIS (International Lesbian Information Service) (Box 9)
      [includes info on the 3rd ILIS conference in Lichtaart, Belgium, 12/30/81-1/3/82; 5th conf. in Paris, 4/1-4/83; 8th conf. in Geneva, 3/28-31/86]
    - Women in Other Countries (Box 9)
  - Third World Women's Groups Subseries
    - Atlanta Groups, Activities, etc. (Box 9)
    - In US (Box 9)
    - National Black Women's Health Project [see "Local Women's Groups"] (Box 9)
    - In Other Countries (Box 9)
    - Black Women and Women's Movement (Box 10)
    - Black Lesbians (Box 10)
      [2 folders; includes biographical fact sheet about Pat Parker; photocopies of photographs of black lesbians, with handwritten information about each; and a photocopy of Black Lesbians: An Annotated Bibliography (74 pp)]
    - Third World Women and "Justice" (Box 10)
    - Dessie X. Woods (Box 10)
      [an African-American woman convicted on 2/12/76 of manslaughter and robbery and sentenced to 22 years in prison for the fatal shooting of Ronnie Horne, an armed white rapist. File contains info about case and defense fund (See also "Third World Women and Justice")]
  - Film and Video Subseries
    - Film and Video Information (Box 10)
    - Lesbian/Gay Film Catalogs (Box 10)
    - Third World Film Catalogs (Box 10)
    - Other Film Catalogs - Non-Gay, Non-Women (Box 10)
    - Women's Film Catalogs (Box 10)
  - Theater Subseries
    - Feminist Theater, Arts, Etc. (Box 10)
  - Archives and Collections Subseries
    - Straight Archives/Gay Subgroups (Box 10)
    - American Library Association Gay Task Force [see also Box 16, under "Gay Groups (Regional and National)"] (Box 10)
    - Archives - Lesbian and Gay (Box 10)
    - Lesbian Herstory Archives (Box 10)
    - Third World Women's Archives (Box 10)
    - Women's History Research Center (Box 10)
    - Atlanta Ad Hoc Committee for the Preservation of Atlanta's Lesbian and Gay History (Box 10)
    - National Council for Research on Women (Box 10)
    - Women's Libraries and Collections (Box 10)
  - Resorts Subseries (Box 10)
    - Women's Tours and Trips (Box 10)
    - Women's Yellow Pages - Massachusetts (Box 10)
    - Cultural Resorts (Gay and Lesbian) (Box 10)
    - Cultural Resorts (Lesbian): Pagoda (Box 10)
  - Grants Subseries
    - Granting Sources [see also Box 1] (Box 10)
    - Grant Writing (Box 10)
  - Media Subseries (Box 11)
    - Photography (Box 11)
    - Tips in Dealing with the Media (Box 11)
    - NGTF (National Gay Task Force) Media (Box 11)
      [Press Releases; see also Box 16, under "Gay Groups (Regional and National)"]
    - Radio and Cable TV: Women and Gay (Box 11)
    - Misc. Journal/Constitution articles concerning women (Box 11)
    - Atlanta Journal/Constitution Coverage - General (Box 11)
    - Women and The Media - Advertising (Box 11)
    - Women's Forums, Dialogues, and Speeches (Box 11)
  - Literature, Bibliographies and Reading Lists Subseries
    - Black Women's Bibliographies and Reading Lists (Box 11)
    - Book Reviews, Movies Reviews, TV (Box 11)
    - Children's Literature (Box 11)
    - Lesbian/Gay Bibliographies and Reading Lists (Box 11)
    - Other Bibliographies [progressive movements] (Box 11)
    - Poetry (Box 11)
    - Sexuality Bibliographies (Box 11)
    - Women Bibliographies and Reading Lists (Box 11)
    - Women and Writers (Box 11)
    - Authors (Box 11)
  - Publishers Subseries
    - Gay and Lesbian, Homosexuality - catalogs, etc. (Box 11)
    - Lesbian/Feminist Catalogs (Box 11)
    - Women Publishers and Presses
      - Diana Press (Box 11)
      - The Feminist Press (Box 11)
      - KNOW, Inc. (Box 12)
        [A feminist publishing collective founded in 1969 by members of the Pittsburgh, PA chapter of NOW, KNOW, Inc. published and distributed reprints of feminist articles; books relating to women's work, women's studies and women's liberation; and their newsletter, Know News. NOTE: Book titles published by KNOW, Inc. have been individually catalogued; check the on-line catalog.]
      - Know News, 1973-1976 (Box 12)
      - Misc Flyers (Box 12)
        (includes a list of women's rights organizations, presses, newsletters, and special publications)
      - Catalogs and Price Lists (Box 12)
      - Reprinted articles and papers. (Box 12)
        Over 100 items, includes classics such as Pat Mainardi's The Politics of Housework, Jo Freeman's Origins of the Women's Liberation Movement, Kathi Roche's The Secretary: Capitalism's House Nigger, Anne Koedt's The Myth of the Vaginal Orgasm, and Woman-Identified Woman, by the Radicalesbians
      - Naiad Press (Box 12)
      - Non-Women/Gay-specific (Box 12)
  - Bookstores Subseries
    - Women's and Gay Bookstores (Box 12)
  - Merchandise Subseries (Box 12)
    (Catalogs for feminist and/or lesbian/gay posters, buttons, T-Shirts, jewelry, calendars)
  - Music Subseries [see also Boxes 22-24, Orchid Productions/Lucina's Music]
    - Music Catalogs, Misc. (Box 12)
    - Lady Slipper Catalogs (Box 12)
    - Olivia Records (Box 12)
    - Michigan Womyn's Music Festival (Box 12)
    - Misc. Music Festivals (Box 12)
    - Music References (Box 12)
    - Music and Songs (Box 12)
    - Southern Women's Music and Comedy Festival [see also Box 29] (Box 12)
  - Theory/Analysis (Women) Subseries (Box 13)
    - Early Women's liberation and "The Movement" (Box 13)
    - Women's Liberation Movement (Box 13)
      [donated by Donna J. Brogan (then Donna Brogan Ruhl), older sister of Linda L. Brogan ( 1944-1983 ), both early feminists in Chapel Hill/Durham Women's Liberation Movement, ca. 1968-1974 ]
    - Analysis of the Women's Movement (Box 13)
    - Women's Movement - Theory and Origins (Box 13)
    - Radical Feminism - Movement (Box 13)
    - Bisexuality (Box 13)
    - Biology (Box 13)
    - Feminism and Class (Box 13)
    - Feminism and Marxism (Box 13)
    - Imperialism (Box 13)
    - Consumerism and Women (Box 13)
    - Socialist Feminism (Box 13)
    - Lesbianism and Art: Theory (Box 13)
    - Lesbian Battering (Box 13)
    - Lesbian Herstory (Box 13)
    - Lesbianism - Our Ideology - Development (Box 13)
    - Matriarchy (Box 13)
    - Political Strategies (Box 13)